<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Black Book of Thoughts</title><description>Some random thoughts about life from Klaus Kneupner</description><link>https://kneupner.de</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 21:14:08 +0100</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 21:14:08 +0100</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://kneupner.de/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/people-centric</guid><title>People-Centric Organisation?</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/people-centric</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://decrapifywork.substack.com/i/142862901/little-lies">Colin Newlyn</a> provides this checklist, called <em>Little Lies</em>, but I consider them more blatant lies. So when organisations say they have a ‘people-centric’ culture, you have to look at their actions.</p><ul><li>If they get rid of people to boost short-term profits;</li><li>If they re-organise without any consultation;</li><li>If they have lots of procedures in place to police behaviour;</li><li>If they impose cultural norms;</li><li>If they recruit to for ‘culture fit’;</li><li>If they don’t support flexible working;</li><li>If they unilaterally impose changes in terms and conditions;</li><li>If they cut the training budget to save costs;</li><li>If they tolerate high-performing arseholes;</li><li>If there are topics that are ‘out of bounds’;</li><li>If they continually ask for more to be done with less;</li><li>If they focus on profits;</li><li>If they make you fit the process;</li><li>If they allow workloads and stress to increase; then they are not people-centric. Because if they were, they wouldn’t do those things. By their fruits shall you know them.</li></ul><p>A great list, and I have experienced quite a few myself. I could add a few more, but I think you got the gist.</p><p>I found it via <a href="https://substack.com/redirect/2/eyJlIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly93d3cud29ya2Z1dHVyZXMuaW8vc3Vic2NyaWJlP3V0bV9zb3VyY2U9ZW1haWwmdXRtX2NhbXBhaWduPWVtYWlsLXN1YnNjcmliZSZyPTI5aTI5MyZuZXh0PWh0dHBzJTNBJTJGJTJGd3d3LndvcmtmdXR1cmVzLmlvJTJGcCUyRnRpbWUtYW5kLWVmZm9ydCIsInAiOjE0Mjk0MDYxMSwicyI6MTYsImYiOnRydWUsInUiOjEzNjg5MTYyMywiaWF0IjoxNzExNDU1NDQ3LCJleHAiOjE3MTQwNDc0NDcsImlzcyI6InB1Yi0wIiwic3ViIjoibGluay1yZWRpcmVjdCJ9.zTWKOZ-mSXmHWQRd0SanooRGOM1q78eyjCv4wrVBj94?">workfutures</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/starting-a-consultancy</guid><title>Things to Consider When You Start Your Business</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/starting-a-consultancy</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, I started a consultancy business in Denmark over the last months. Here are a few things that I needed to consider over these previous months. You can use them as a checklist. I cannot comment on how transferable this list is to other countries.</p><p>I don't have any affiliation with the companies mentioned.</p><h2>Company Type</h2><p>It starts with the proper company form. The primary considerations are:</p><ul><li><strong>your risk level</strong>: if you are a limited company in any form (for example in Denmark: ApS) then you can sleep tight. Even if something goes wrong, your private property won't be touched (you better ask your lawyer about the real risk here). If you are doing it for a single-owner approach (enkelmand/VSO), then you are at least theoretically in the risk zone. Depending on your business, this is unlikely, and there are insurances to consider.</li><li><strong>tax implications</strong>: ask your accountant for this. It looks like that not all accountants are created equally, and they might have some detailed knowledge of one or the other type.</li></ul><h2>Bank Account</h2><p>You will need a bank account dedicated to your business. I took Lunar. So far, I like the following:</p><ul><li>The virtual credit card arrives instantaneously and works like a charm.</li><li>Transactions are instantaneous, too. I chose a business account, and you seem to need one if you want to get VAT paid back. My business account has some interesting abilities (not sure about the private accounts):</li><li>It helps you to collect all receipts, and tells you which transaction misses a receipt, and via <a href="https://business.lunar.app/">https://business.lunar.app/</a>, can you get them all in one zip file for the accountant.</li><li>You can share files (receipts, e.g. via email print) towards the Lunar App and attach them to the transaction.</li></ul><h2>Tax Declarations / Accountant</h2><p>With the account comes the necessity to file tax statements. You can do it yourself with software like Billy (they have a valuable ebook to understand this), or you can find an accountant (which is helpful to understand the correct type).</p><h2>Insurances</h2><p>Insurance comes in many forms. I suggest you have a chat with an insurance person early on. You can at least ensure the following:</p><ul><li>Your company's property</li><li>Law support</li><li>#ork accidents</li><li>The consultancy advice you provide</li><li>The products you provide</li></ul><h2>Pension</h2><p>If you were employed before, you need a new pension scheme. In Denmark, these schemes often include some health insurance and disability insurance. Each time you want to increase your insurance level (pay more in, get more out), you must answer health questions and open up all health issues from the last year. But spending a lot from day one might be challenging as you have a low income. Many use PFA via Lederne, but I chose a different one.</p><h2>Buying things from yourself</h2><p>Your company might want to buy your laptop and your working desktop. They might no longer be covered by your home insurance when they are located at home.</p><h2>Phone</h2><p>You might need a new phone number. Or you want to take over your number from your previous employment. There are special work phone tariffs, but they have a three-year binding. So, think about what a regular private contract can do for you.</p><p>One trick I learned along the way was to call them up. In the shop, they can sell you anything, but the phone conversation will be recorded so that they cannot provide you with other things than requested. The result will fit your needs better.</p><h2>Internet</h2><p>You need a new one if you get internet from your previous job. Your phone provider will want to sell you a good deal. But compared with "landline" providers.</p><h2>Review Subscriptions</h2><p>Your company should pay for some of the stuff you have subscribed to.</p><h2>Travel</h2><p>I now got myself a rejsekort for my company (at least I requested one - it takes already over a month). It allows me to have the journeys to and from work paid directly via my company.</p><p>Cars are another way of travelling. I recommend you talk to your accountant.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/tellTheStoryAsIfIwouldBeResponsible</guid><title>Tell the story as if I am responsible</title><description>Learn about an interesting way to think about responsibility.</description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/tellTheStoryAsIfIwouldBeResponsible</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a story where a line manager successfully resolved a problem at work involving two individuals who couldn't work together.</p><p>The manager began by taking responsibility for the problem, acknowledging that she had overlooked it for too long although she was aware of the problem. Then, she asked both parties to share their perspectives as if they were responsible for the issue. (Note: This approach is not be suitable for cases like sexual harassment!)</p><p>Each person was then encouraged to reflect on their own contributions to the problem, rather than blaming the other. When one pointed at the other as a source of the problem the task was renewed. So, instead of "the data from the other person was bad" the task was to point out the own failure: "I didn't check the data before I forwarded". The goal was for everyone to take ownership of their part in the situation. To see how each was contributing to the situation. Situation, going on for months was fixed within days.</p><p>The message is clear: think about what you can do to change the situation. Don't blame others and take responsibility.</p><p>I found this <a href="https://sindresorhus.com/one-thing">little app</a>, it puts a few words in the menu bar of my Mac. It now says (even in red): "Tell the story as if I am responsible".</p><p>This story comes from the interesting <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/51798072">"Upstream" book by Dan Heath</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/on-lifes-choices</guid><title>On Life's Choices</title><description>We have so many possibilities. This is a simple visualisations of it.</description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/on-lifes-choices</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What a gem! <a href="https://twitter.com/waitbutwhy/status/1476962460049584136?s=20&t=PbJtSdcANHmYEeUHRMFi8g">Thanks Tim</a>!</p><img src="images/found/FH83m_aX0AIjFAX.jpeg"/><p>This is actually so true. Yes, loads of roads not taken. But yet, so many possibilities left. Choose what you do. Not acting is as well a choice, and a path not taken. Not necessarily a bad one, but a choice.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/on-success-and-other-people</guid><title>On Success and other people</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/on-success-and-other-people</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found this great quote again. (Thanks to <a href="https://readwise.io">Readwise.io</a>, which btw. creates such nice pictures from the quote)</p><figure><img src="images/found/The-10-Keys-to-Success.png" alt="The 10 Keys to Success by John Bird When you hear people say things like this, you need to take it with a pinch of salt. Much of the time they will say it because they are jealous of you and your courage. They will tell themselves that risk is stupid, that it will only lead to something bad and mess up their lives. So then you come along, all excited and full of energy about doing something new, and they are not pleased. Because they do not want to leave their comfort zone, the idea of you doing so is very scary. It reminds them that they have dreams they want to follow, dreams they don't have the courage or guts to chase."/> <figcaption>Fantastic observation from John Bird</figcaption></figure><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bird,_Baron_Bird">John Bird</a> wrote a few remarkable books of which I were given two over 10 years ago. His way of life was clearly a different from mine and from most people reading this page. I recommend his books. They are quick to read but very insightful.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/sitting-in-the-right-box</guid><title>Sitting in the right box</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/sitting-in-the-right-box</link><pubDate>Sun, 2 May 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We all have our lessons learned. We all draw on some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meme">memes</a> that describe how you think about life in general. At least, that is how I work. A few ideas that got stuck with me, rang a chord and that will be used to explain life or at least patterns seen.</p><p>And this is one that I use consistently. It not only stuck because of the drawing. Here it is:</p><img src="images/thoughts/rightBox.jpeg"/><p>The heading says "it all depends on sitting in the right box". Left box offers chicks for cuddling - the right box offers shark fodder both at the same price.</p><p>Whoever did this was a genius. It explains so many things. Just think of rich vs poor parents, born in a rich country with access to Corona vaccination or not. Or think of the great teacher in your parallel class, the genetic disposition of someone, etc.</p><p>Now, I am not saying that everything in life is luck. I neither say that you should accept your box as a stoic. Of course, you need to work on your life. Of course, an initial disadvantage might proof to become the challenge that eventually changes you into a better person - and the like.</p><p>But it still is very much a game of luck.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/on-happiness</guid><title>On Happiness</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/on-happiness</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I love this talk on the topic of happiness from Shawn Anchor. It is funny and teaches some important messages. Did you ever hear the advice to write every day three things down you are grateful for? This talk explains it.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://embed.ted.com/talks/shawn_achor_the_happy_secret_to_better_work" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/celeste-headlee-on-conversations</guid><title>Celeste Headlee on Conversations</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/celeste-headlee-on-conversations</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn't know Celeste before. This <a href="https://www.ted.com/speakers/celeste_headlee">link</a> provides a quick introduction. She talks about the value of conversations and how to create valuable conversations.</p><p>Among the great content does Celeste mention some really good quotes. My favourites are:</p><ul><li><em>“Everyone you will ever meet knows something that you don’t” (Bill Nye)</em> I saw this quote before, but this time it struck a cord. Clearly, everyone is worth listening to!</li><li><em>“No man ever listened himself out of a job." (Calvin Coolidge</em>) "Speech is silver, silence is gold", but somehow more colorful.</li><li><em>“Most people do not listen with the intent to understand; they listen with the intent to reply.” (Stephen R. Covey</em>) Guilty</li></ul><p>The 10 tips in short:</p><ol><li>Don’t multitask – be present</li><li>Don’t pontificate - be humble and learn from others</li><li>Ask open-ended questions – start with who, what, when, where, why or how</li><li>Go with the flow – whatever you think of, let it go</li><li>If you don’t know, say that you don’t know - have integrity</li><li>Don’t equate your experience with theirs – all experiences are individual – it is NOT about you</li><li>Try not to repeat yourself – it’s condescending and boring</li><li>Stay out of the weeds - don’t get stuck in details</li><li>Listen – this is the most important one</li><li>Be brief!</li></ol>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/brene-brown-on-vulnerability</guid><title>Brené Brown on Vulnerability</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/brene-brown-on-vulnerability</link><pubDate>Fri, 6 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My first reaction to this video is that I met in my life 3 times people that were able to laugh about themselves. They were making themselves vulnerable, telling me how stupid they have been again and again and laughed about themselves - (hopefully) knowing that I wouldn't think less of them (quite the opposite). Do I need to tell you that I admire them? Why else would I count? They are warm and I can be a bit more myself in their company.</p><p>I simply don't think myself being capable of this (yet). But this is the way to go! See this video for yourself.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://embed.ted.com/talks/brene_brown_the_power_of_vulnerability" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p>Brené Brown's: The Power of Vulnerability</p><p>Great talk, thanks Brené.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/watch-a-video-starting-with-the-line-call-me-an-idiot-and-learn-something-about-bullying</guid><title>Watch a video starting with the line "call me an idiot" and learn something about bullying</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/watch-a-video-starting-with-the-line-call-me-an-idiot-and-learn-something-about-bullying</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There isn't much to say. I like the performance and I like the way it is explained by Brooks Gibbs. And I know it works.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G8l3dMjdmzc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/learn-unlearn</guid><title>Learn &amp; Unlearn</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/learn-unlearn</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Great Video with some insights to your brain. Enjoy!</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MFzDaBzBlL0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/genghis-khan-savages-to-conquer-the-world</guid><title>Genghis Khan: Savages to conquer the world?</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/genghis-khan-savages-to-conquer-the-world</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 1979 there was an interesting Song as part of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision_Song_Contest_1979">European Song Contest</a>: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dschinghis_Khan_(song)">Dschinghis Khan.</a> I was a little boy of 5 years but the melody got stuck in my head. The lyrics suggested that the Mongols were some kind of primitives. Later, I heard about the Mongol invasion into Europe and something did sound wrong: how can a group of savages run over half of Europe and a huge part of Asia? Every war I have heard of showed that wars are costly activities. And your armies overextend themselves, they bleed out, etc. So, how could a hardly known group of nomads rule most of the known world within 1 or 2 generations? And how could it happen that they ruled big empires for over 150 years, even ruling the Chinese, the most advanced nation of that time?</p><p>I recently read the great book "<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/93426.Genghis_Khan_and_the_Making_of_the_Modern_World">Genghis Khan and the Making of the Modern World</a>" by Jack Weatherford (ISBN13: 9780609809648). The book has a good explanation. Mongols might have had a rough life, but they were not savages. Prior to Genghis Khan they were only absorbed in fighting themselves. Genghis Khan was the man who became supreme leader of all Mongols. And his methods were far from primitive, although often brutal. He was breaking with traditions time after time but kept enough to create a strong coherence.</p><p>So far, so interesting. Now, how could the joint Mongols conquer everything? Well, according to the book, the Mongols used their superior battle skills, but incorporated all strategies that they could find. E.g. they must have had brilliant engineers, building all kind of siege weapons in short time. They were smart enough to "hire" more engineers in the conquered areas. They used fear as a weapon. But the one story that did explain the above questions to me was about the expedition into Europe. Whilst in Europe much emphasis was on honour and fighting bravely during battle, <strong>the Mongol's emphasis was on winning</strong>. So, imagine a European army that is ready to fight, like at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Legnica">Battle of Legnica</a>. The Mongols start a bit of fighting but then retreat. The Europeans thought they have won (why would the enemy flee otherwise?) and charge after the Mongols and overextending themselves, separating cavalry from infantry. The Mongols were just keeping out of range on their enduring horses and when the chasing army was completely disordered changed direction again and killing everyone with their long distance bows with minimal human costs to their own army. In addition the Mongols were using smoke in combination shouting "Run/Flee" in the language of the opponent to add to the confusion. This was strategy, using the weakness of the enemy, their believe in honour, their bad organisation. And it seems like the Mongols have adjusted their strategy each time. With this approach the Mongols could conquer everything.</p><p>The book highlights many other interesting achievements, whether in battle, or regarding religious freedom, regarding society or regarding organisation. Organisation by the way was the reason the wars were an economical success for the Mongols and they kept in power for a long time.</p><p>I have too little knowledge to confirm any of the many points of the book. It might not be exactly scientific, but what it does get across is that the Mongols were no primitive savages. To be as successful as they were they needed to outsmart their enemies on a regular base and overcome the paradigms of their time.</p><p>So, what are the lessons learned?</p><ol><li>If something sounds odd, start digging. There is a reason. It might be a simple misunderstanding, or it might be that you only hear a part of the story. Which part was left out and why?</li><li>If you are willing to leave from your traditions and are willing to learn you can conquer the world. Of course you need luck. Of course one cannot just repeat a story like Genghis Khans. But you hear regular stories about individuals that are creating amazing impact. And normally you hear that they have broken with "known" paradigms.</li></ol><p>By the way, the impact of the Mongols on the course of world was potentially bigger than one thought of. Whilst Central Europe ultimately got lucky and wasn't affected that much, the Mongols had a huge impact on Islam, changing the course of Islam to my (limited) knowledge. There was even a connection between the distribution of the black death and the commerce/road network in the Mongol empire. But not all impact was negative. Many ideas got born and ideas got distributed. Life would be different today. And all that because one man - with luck - took on the world, adapting to the circumstances whenever needed.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/rejection-therapy</guid><title>Rejection Therapy</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/rejection-therapy</link><pubDate>Mon, 7 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some people are my personal heroes. Jia Jiang is a great example of someone who overcame his issues (fear of rejection) by direct confrontation. He mastered his demon, learned something about human nature and is able to tell you his story with humor. It blew me.</p><p>https://www.ted.com/talks/jia_jiang_what_i_learned_from_100_days_of_rejection</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/how-i-handle-long-email-delays</guid><title>How I Handle Long Email Delays</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/how-i-handle-long-email-delays</link><pubDate>Tue, 1 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found the below the other day. https://waitbutwhy.com/2016/03/long-email-delay.html</p><p>If it wouldn't be so sad, it would be really funny. I think most people have gone through this behaviour. Good to know that other people worry too much as well. :-)</p><p>In case you don't know "<a href="https://waitbutwhy.com">Wait But Why</a>" yet, then you should clearly have a look. I wrote earlier about the <a href="https://kneupner.de/howteslawillchangeyourlife">Tesla article</a> from the same site.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/how-to-live-a-remarkable-life-in-a-conventional-world</guid><title>How to Live a Remarkable life in a Conventional World</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/how-to-live-a-remarkable-life-in-a-conventional-world</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever thought that a 9 to 5 job isn't the right thing for you? Did you ever get impressed by all the stories about the really successful people and how they often didn't study? Did you think that you should do something totally different, but for a number of reasons you are stuck with what you do?</p><p>I know, very pathetic. But I guess we all have similar thoughts from time to time. And some people are struggling even more with these thoughts. I met plenty of people with non-traditional CVs, not following the standard path of life. And I could imagine that they would especially like this document, but not only them: "<a href="https://chrisguillebeau.com/3x5/files/2008/06/worlddomination.pdf">A Brief Guide to World Domination* - How to Live a Remarkable life in a Conventional World *and other important goals</a>" written by <a href="https://chrisguillebeau.com/">Chris Guillebeau</a>. I like the style - especially the humour that is already shown in the title. But I recommend it for the content which is actually thought-provoking. In essence it's a call for "start with the end in mind", and then work against the end, based on your key strength.</p><p>I have seen most of the content before, but as we know a different presentation will lead to different results. This presentation triggered me to think about the two key questions of the document. Thanks Chris!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/storytelling-in-a-nutshell</guid><title>Storytelling in a Nutshell</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/storytelling-in-a-nutshell</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I came across this great infographic regarding storytelling.</p><img src="https://tedconfblog.files.wordpress.com/2013/11/andrewstanton-ted_poster_translated_v21.jpg" alt="Storytelling in a Nutshell"/><p>] <em>The Clues to a Great Story</em></p><p>(https://blog.ted.com/how-to-tell-a-great-story-visualized/) Why do I like it? It's visual, and it puts a structure on something that you know implicitly yourself but you might not have found the pattern.</p><p>Source: https://blog.ted.com/how-to-tell-a-great-story-visualized/</p><p>In case you want to know more, I suggest that you read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hero_with_a_Thousand_Faces">The Hero with a thousand Faces</a>. But be warned, it's a tough read, simply because it is now (due to this book?) so obvious.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/goals-and-measures</guid><title>Goals and Measures</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/goals-and-measures</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let's look at goals and how a good measure is supportive to the goal. I will connect a few things that I have learned over time.</p><p>Andrey Salomatin writes about Theory of Constraints (TOC) and applies it to Software development. So far, he has 3 articles: <a href="https://medium.com/@flpvsk/systems-thinking-in-management-c3ed049e8d91">Systems thinking in management</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@flpvsk/work-hard-enough-and-you-wont-finish-anything-d631d65e7478">Work hard enough and you won’t finish anything</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@flpvsk/i-bet-you-look-good-on-the-plant-floor-b0c335212eca">I bet you look good on the plant floor</a>. Well worth reading.</p><p>However, the one that really triggered me thinking was the first: <a href="https://medium.com/@flpvsk/systems-thinking-in-management-c3ed049e8d91">Systems thinking in management</a>. I am not sure whether I ever thought about it before, but he has a nice phrase in his article:</p><blockquote><p>Goal has nothing to do with System’s internals. Look for it outside of the System.</p></blockquote><p>One of his examples (he has more) is an airplane. Airplanes don't exists to fly (internal), they exists in order to let people travel fast from A to B (outside). Good one. But he got further. He was describing a situation where misaligned measures are contra productive to the goal of the system. Measure get misaligned when internal goals are prioritised over external goals. Instead of using his example would I like to describe the story that I heard earlier and that made this article so relevant to me.</p><p>I once was on an Enterprise Architecture conference where I was lucky enough to listen to <a href="https://www.bptrends.com/about/advisors/roger-burlton/">Roger Burton</a>. He told a story about a global manufacturing company that was his client (he didn't provide a name but a hint that we would all know it). The board of that manufacturer wanted to reduce the time from the order until the customer got the ordered goods. For some 2 years all the programmes to improve that time didn't help. He was looking at the problem from a measure perspective. His philosophie behind that was the simple "mantra":</p><blockquote><p>You get the process you are measuring.</p></blockquote><p>So, people will adjust their processes in order to improve the measures. If your salary is connected to a measure, wouldn't you do the same?</p><p>What were the measures in Roger's example?</p><ul><li>Sales team members got a bonus for every order coming in in the last 2 days of the month (one can easily imagine how this one started). This meant that sales people whenever possible delayed the order in order to get it placed at the end of month (reinforcing the perceived need for this incentive). Result? First delay for the customer.</li><li>Production team was measured on costs. How do you drive down costs? Increase batch size! So, production team was delaying production of goods in order to increase batch size.</li><li>The next one was internal logistic, it was a global manufacturer after all, so unfinished goods needed to be send regularly between plants. How do you drive down logistic costs? Fill the truck/container. What was logistics measure on? Cost. Does waiting to fill the container improve total turnover time?</li></ul><p>He only named these 3, but I can easily see how other departments were working against misaligned goals, too. Roger's story ended with the comment that the board was seeing improvements quickly once the measures were aligned with the goal of the company, to reduce order-to-delivery time.</p><p>Align your measures with your goals. The goal is not within your department. Not even within your company. If you want to make money by selling, you are already misaligned. Your customer's benefits are what you need to measure against. Which, interestingly enough, was the topic of my <a href="https://kneupner.de/whose-success-i-worry">previous post</a>.</p><p>By the way, I found Andrey's articles through my current favourite blog, <a href="http://www.jackvinson.com/">Knowledge Jolt with Jack.</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/whose-success-i-worry</guid><title>Whose success do I worry about?</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/whose-success-i-worry</link><pubDate>Sun, 3 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found a little gem to share: <a href="http://www.jackvinson.com/blog/2017/11/12/whose-success-do-i-worry-about">http://www.jackvinson.com/blog/2017/11/12/whose-success-do-i-worry-about.</a> It's a simple twist that changes your perspective. Think about your customers needs, not your needs if you want to succeed in the long run.</p><p>On a related note, sometimes I observe the same mentality within a company where I see decisions made that seem to serve personal interest more than the interests of the company. It seems to have less negative impact as these people tend to change their customer base completely whenever they are switching jobs.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/vithanco-concept-maps</guid><title>Vithanco Concept Maps - An Editor for Concept Maps</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/vithanco-concept-maps</link><pubDate>Thu, 8 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I created a little tool that will help you creating Concept maps. It is available at the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/visual-thinking-with-concept-maps/id1246432524?mt=12">Mac App Store</a>. Vithanco stands for "Visual Thinking and Communication".</p><p>Concept Maps are one of my standard artefacts of projects or whenever I need to understand a new area. They help to define the vocabulary by setting all relevant terms into relation to each other.</p><figure><img src="images/thoughts/Unsaved-Vithanco-Concept-Maps-Document.jpg"/> <figcaption>What is a Concept Map?</figcaption></figure><p>Such a way of defining a vocabulary is (to my experience) superior to a traditional dictionary where you find a paragraph regarding the meaning of a word. Why? Simply because I have never seen anyone reading a 10 page document of definitions without the mind wandering off. A Concept Map in contrast is something that everyone can concentrate on. And by creating verifiable sentences you can double-check each relationship in a simple and constructive way. Just create a set of concept maps and take every new project member through each relationship. You will be able to align the meaning of the terms. What if the other person disagrees on a sentence? Great! You just hit a misalignment that might become problematic at a later stage. Align on how to use the terms. As I said, it's a communication tool.</p><img src="images/thoughts/Jedi-3.png"/><p>Look <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concept_map">here</a> if you are interested in learning more about Concept Maps.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/vithanco-ibis</guid><title>Vithanco IBIS - An Editor for the IBIS Notation</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/vithanco-ibis</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>What is the IBIS Notation?</h2><p>Use visuals to help you thinking. Vithanco IBIS is an editor for diagrams that use the IBIS Notation.</p><figure><img src="images/thoughts/Screenshot-1.png" alt="Main Concepts of IBIS notation and Visual Thinking with IBIS"/> <figcaption>Annotated Screenshot from "Visual Thinking with IBIS"</figcaption></figure><p>The Issue-Based Information System (IBIS) Notation was invented by Werner Kunz and Horst Rittel as an argumentation-based approach to support analysis of so-called "wicked" problems. However, IBIS Notation can be used for all problems, whether wicked or not.</p><p>This app creates and changes IBIS diagrams in order to map out a dialogue/argumentation or a thought/analysis. It uses a simple structure to help you getting to the bottom of your problems.</p><p>The IBIS Notation is a simple graphical presentation of questions and answers with their respective advantages and disadvantages with the following rules:</p><ul><li>A question can have any number of answers or ideas.</li><li>Any answer/idea can have any number of arguments for each answer, split into the two categories of pros and cons.</li></ul><p>The result is a simple graphical representation of a question. You can use it for any kind of question and you have a short exploration of a topic. It is of interest for all those that prefer a graphical representation instead of a textual description.</p><p>The concept of the IBIS notation are deliberately kept simple to make it useful for many use cases. The only so-to-say “complication” is that you can attach a question to any other item. As such you can:</p><ul><li>question a question (“Shouldn’t we rather discuss X?” or “What are the assumptions behind this question?”), or you can</li><li>question an answer (“To follow this idea, what would we need to take into consideration?”, “What proof do we have for this statement?”), or you can</li><li>question a pro or con (“What could we do to overcome this disadvantage?”).</li></ul><p>Each of these questions would then have it’s own structure with answers/ideas and pros&amp;cons. And of course can these have further questions attached. Nothing restricts how big the IBIS diagram might become. You as the creator decide how many questions you want to include asks and how “deep” you want to go with your diagram in order to analyse the topic at hand.</p><p>Have a look at the annotated Screenshot above. I used my tool to describe itself.</p><h2>And why would you use IBIS?</h2><p>Again, I use the tool to describe itself.</p><img src="images/thoughts/Why-IBIS.png" alt="Why using IBIS Notation"/><h2>What can you do with the Editor?</h2><p>Vithanco IBIS supports the creation of IBIS graphs in the following ways.</p><img src="images/thoughts/Edit-your-IBIS-Graph-4.png" alt="Change your IBIS Notation graph with the editor"/><p>I will go into more details over time.</p><h2>Helpfile for IBIS Editor</h2><p>You can simply use the help function within the application. But you can as well access the content here: <a href="https://kneupner.de/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IBISHelp.pdf">IBISHelp.pdf</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/benefit-realisation</guid><title>A useful Benefit Realisation Approach</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/benefit-realisation</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the big topics for every project organisation (and IT in particular) is benefit realisation. Whenever I think about benefits then I think about the approach from <a href="http://www.som.cranfield.ac.uk/som/dinamic-content/research/documents/peppardwarddaniel07.pdf">Peppard, Ward, and Daniel</a> that I found a few years back. Ever since am I working on making it happen and at the time of writing (Jan 2017) I might be able to get a first version implemented within a few weeks.</p><p>The basic ideas of the article are captured in this mind map.</p><img src="https://kneupner.de/images/thoughts/Managing-the-Realization-of-Business-Benefits-from-IT-Investments.png" alt="Benefit Realisation according to Peppard, Ward, and Daniel"/><p>A <a href="https://kneupner.de/images/thoughts/Managing-the-Realization-of-Business-Benefits-from-IT-Investments-bw.png">B&amp;W version</a> is also available.</p><h2>Advantages of the Approach</h2><p>Why am I liking this so much? Because it combines several elements that I know to be true:</p><ul><li>People need to be accountable if you want to succeed. Too many projects have nobody being accountable for benefits as benefit realisation starts often after the end of the project. The project enables the benefits, but it takes a while to get new processes running smoothly in order to realise benefits. And at that time the project team might no longer exists. This approach makes the right people accountable. And those are normally not within the project team. Btw, this is a good argument for the <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2015/03/15/heres-what-fail-fast-really-means/">fail fast</a> concept.</li><li><a href="https://www.stephencovey.com/7habits/7habits-habit2.php">Start with the end in mind</a>: most projects are supposed to fix an issue or improve some specific processes. When we know this then we can start with analysing the intended benefits and then simply plan backwards: what needs to change in order to create these benefits? The other way around, that you have a new technology and then try to make use of it, is much more rare.</li><li>If you care about something then you need to track and monitor it. If you care about benefits then it's simply not enough to define benefits in the business case for the project. Instead you need to use the benefits as the guiding principle throughout the project. I therefore started looking at the BDN (Benefit Dependency Network) suggested by the authors as a "Benefit Breakdown Structure" as replacement for the "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Product_breakdown_structure">Product Breakdown Structure</a>" or "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_breakdown_structure">Work Breakdown Structure</a>". It's not a perfect fit as the BDN is not a tree structure but you can easily match it.</li><li>Projects benefit (no pun intended) if key stakeholder participate and are actively involved. This approach turns the benefit owners into project stakeholders. If you do it right then their accountability will turn them into valuable assets that have a keen interest in the project to succeed. However, see my comment further below regarding politics involved.</li></ul><h2>Considerations for Implementation</h2><p>If you are looking into this then you need to ensure that you understand what is a portfolio activity (maintaining a Benefit Registry) and what is a project activity (identifying benefits, adjusting project plan to change of benefits).</p><p>I am wondering for some time now why this concept is not yet in use everywhere. I believe that the problem is of political nature. Not everybody likes to be accountable. And it can be of dis-benefit for a benefit owner not to have a project to blame for non-realisation of benefits. It might therefore not be in the interest of middle management to follow this approach.</p><p>Clearly, if you are just wondering about work breakdown structures after reading this article, then there are many implementation tools readily available. I found <a href="http://w1.msonr.net/prod/53082dab-4f50-4237-b65a-34cbeb272e82/15c39af9-eb6c-4d31-b4a3-72697c7aa5c4">this guide</a> which made a good impression on me.</p><p><strong>[Update 25/9/2017]:</strong> I found <a href="http://itsadeliverything.com/benefits-map-impact-mapping-for-programme-managers">this</a> interesting article. Triggered by the Managing Successful Programs (MSP) course did I realise that Benefit Maps are quite well known. At least much better than I thought. Ward et. al. have "just" honed the idea from the IT perspective (not sure in which order these ideas were introduced, I will need to research this).</p><p>Steven is touching on another interesting and related topic: Impact Mapping! It fits quite nicely together as impact mapping is clearly overlapping with benefit mapping. How? I will explain in a later update.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/the-coaching-habit</guid><title>The Coaching Habit Mind Map</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/the-coaching-habit</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the more interesting things in life is coaching. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coaching">Coaching</a> is an activity between two people were one person helps the other person to find answers (and sometimes the right questions) her/himself. The concept fits well with my experience that you cannot tell somebody to change. But with coaching you might help the other person to want to change. Or you actually learn more about the situation (consider "<a href="https://www.stephencovey.com/7habits/7habits-habit5.php">seek first to understand then to be understood</a>") and realise that the other person doesn't need to change, maybe that you should be the one to change.</p><p>However, my coaching skills are by far not good enough. And here I found a book, that provides guidance by providing a set of seven simple questions that can carry a lot of the coaching load. The questions make sense and provide a simple framework for any coaching session. And by providing a framework they allow me to listen better since I don't need to consider a witty next question.</p><p>The book in question is Michael Bungay Stanier's "<a href="http://www.boxofcrayons.biz/the-coaching-habit-book/">The Coaching Habit - Say Less, Ask More &amp; Change the Way You Lead Forever</a>", published in 2016 by Box of Crayons Press. And as usually, I created a Mind Map in order to revisit the good book. I hope you like the book and the Map.</p><figure><img src="https://kneupner.de/images/thoughts/The-Coaching-Habit.png"/> <figcaption>The Coaching Habit Mind Map</figcaption></figure><p>Or download the file either as <a href="https://kneupner.de/images/thoughts/The-Coaching-Habit.png">Colour version</a> or as <a href="https://kneupner.de/images/thoughts/The-Coaching-Habit-BnW.png">B&amp;W version</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/learning-technique-according-james-altucher</guid><title>Learning Technique according to James Altucher</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/learning-technique-according-james-altucher</link><pubDate>Wed, 4 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/10-Step-Learning-Technique.png"/><p>I found a rather interesting article in the web that combined a few things that I was aware of myself and added a bit that I didn’t know before. As usually, I made a Mind Map to capture the key thoughts.</p><p>The original article is <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/05/11/the-only-technique-to-learn-so.html">here</a>. Clearly, some unnecessary exaggeration (like: 10 power 10 times more efficient), but the overall ideas are mostly sane. ;-)</p><p>For printing purposes, there is a <a href="images/visuals/10-Step-Learning-Technique-BW.png">black &amp; white</a> version.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/redesigning-my-site</guid><title>Redesigning my Site</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/redesigning-my-site</link><pubDate>Wed, 4 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Please notice that this page is undergoing some changes. Old content will be a made available again once all the under the hood changes are complete.</p><p>I have changed from Rapidweaver to a Wordpress blog. So far I am very happy about this change but it comes along with a quite some manual work. At the same time I am making some conceptional changes in order for the content to be presented in a way that I like better - and I hope you too.</p><p>Please let me know what you think so far.</p><p>[Update] Interesting enough this isn't the first move of my site. In September 2012 I had the entry below. RapidWeaver was quite an disappointment after some years of slow updates that only costed a lot of money for no real benefit. And I just looked at my old blog. It still exists. Interesting. But here the old entry.</p><p>I started using <a href="http://www.realmacsoftware.com/rapidweaver/">RapidWeaver</a> for this webpage (previously I used iWeb and Blogger) and I am in the process of transferring the content from my old blog page here. Therefore some content will be missing here for some time.</p><p>Unfortunately, this is a manual process that will take some time. In the meanwhile have a look at my old blog page: <a href="http://blackbookofthoughts.blogspot.dk">http://blackbookofthoughts.blogspot.dk</a></p><p>Why did I switch? Unfortunately, iWeb is no longer supported. And I wanted to make some changes that iWeb didn’t support. After some analysis I decided on RapidWeaver is the best available solution for me. One of the biggest problems that I faced during the change was that I wanted to keep the minimalistic style from my old web page. Thankfully, there is <a href="http://www.themeflood.com/">ThemeFlood</a>. ThemeFlood showed the way and the further adoption was reasonable easy.</p><p><strong>Update 26.7.2023</strong> Six years later the next step: from Wordpress to a Static Website, developed with Publish.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/crucial-conversations</guid><title>Crucial Conversations - Mind Map and thoughts</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/crucial-conversations</link><pubDate>Sun, 1 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/thoughts/Crucial-Conversations-2.png"/><p>This Mind Map is based on the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15014.Crucial_Conversations">Crucial Conversation Book</a> from the VitalSmarts people. I simply love the book. I refer to it on a regular base. I re-read it regularly. I believe in the concepts that are explained - even if it doesn't mean that I am now suddenly the best person to tackle all conversations.</p><p>In particular the "path to action" concept is relevant for me. I recognise that the "story that we tell ourselves" is the gap that Stephen Cowley is talking about in his <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1044141.The_8th_Habit">8th habit book</a> between input and response. And I believe the "story" concept to be highly relevant to understand the gap.</p><p>In case you want to print the mind map, here is a <a href="http://kneupner.de/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Crucial-Conversations-BW.png">black &amp; white version</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/what-do-people-want</guid><title>What do people want?</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/what-do-people-want</link><pubDate>Sun, 2 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It just happened today that I realised that two very different books I am reading / processing had two related insights.</p><p>From “<a href="http://www.boxofcrayons.biz/the-coaching-habit-book/">The Coaching Habit: Say Less, Ask More &amp; Change the Way You Lead Forever</a>” by Michael Bungay Stanier, talking about the question “What do you want?”: <strong>“Here’s why the question is so difficult to answer. We often don’t know what we actually want.”</strong></p><p>Now, combine this with “<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16115612-and-the-mountains-echoed">And the Mountains Echoed</a>” by Khaled Hosseini - <strong>“People mostly have it backward. They think they live by what they want. But really what guides them is what they’re afraid of. What they don’t want.”</strong></p><p>What a day to find such related pearls of wisdom.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/howteslawillchangeyourlife</guid><title>How Tesla will Change your Life</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/howteslawillchangeyourlife</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to make you aware of <a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2015/06/how-tesla-will-change-your-life.html">this great blog</a> entry that is named similar as this posting. The author (Tim Urban) goes a lot deeper than many other articles that I have seen on this topic. It is a homage to Elon Musk and his Tesla company, but you get a lot more out of it. Having known most of it I am still impressed. Well researched, nicely elaborated on the context, skilfully put together.</p><p>Why am I so impressed by this article? Because the article goes way beyond the usual superficial answers. It is the best application of the "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_Whys">5 Whys Model</a>" that I have seen so far. The outset of the article is about the Tesla car company. But to provide the full understanding of the material the author goes back to evolution.</p><p>The authors <a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/">blog</a> is worth looking at.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/the-dancing-consumer-model-guy</guid><title>The Dancing Guy, Second Interpretation</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/the-dancing-consumer-model-guy</link><pubDate>Wed, 9 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I already posted this video earlier as an example course in leadership. But now I found a second interpretation around consumer adoption.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed//izP5n1SBEaI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p>Some background to this version: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technology_adoption_lifecycle">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technology_adoption_lifecycle</a> (Moore's Chasm version is an adoption of Rogers's version)</p><p>Which version do you like better? And now we need to think, is the guy with the green shirt the first follower or the first customer? If he is the first customer then what did he buy? Or is there no real difference between first follower or first customer.</p><p>Did you find a 3rd interpretation?</p><p>Please let me know…</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/what-the-heck-is-arbejdsglaede</guid><title>What the heck is Arbejdsglæde?</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/what-the-heck-is-arbejdsglaede</link><pubDate>Sat, 2 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found a lovely video that I simply have to share. It is about happiness at work. And I strongly believe that the key message is right: “Don’t chase success, chase happiness”. But see yourself.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6uxu-wiYsYU" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p>If you like it too then you can find out more here: <a href="http://whattheheckisarbejdsglaede.com/">http://whattheheckisarbejdsglaede.com/</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/aaron-swartz-curiosity</guid><title>Aaron Swartz on Curiosity</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/aaron-swartz-curiosity</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found the following paragraph from an email exchange of Aaron Swartz. Aaron died unfortunately recently. I hardly knew about him before his untimely death, but I recommend reading about him. The following was ringing a chord in me. I have a similar feeling about exploring the world. Once you know a bit about an area, this area is getting interesting. I worked in several industries and did different degrees and it always works for me.</p><p>E.g. when I was about to finish my computer science studies I was looking for a job, maybe Ph.D. I was never exposed to the fascination of mechanical engineerings before and I only went to talk to the people that offered a Ph.D. to computer scientists within engineering simply because I was already working as a student in the same building and I needed job hunting practice anyway. But what I saw fascinated me. My curiosity was stirred. A month later I started an Dr.-Ing. I never regretted that.</p><p>This is what Aaron wrote on curiosity. I might not have been as consequent as he was. :-)</p><blockquote><p>“When I was a kid, I thought a lot about what made me different from the other kids. I don't think I was smarter than them and I certainly wasn't more talented. And I definitely can't claim I was a harder worker -- I've never worked particularly hard, I've always just tried doing things I find fun. Instead, what I concluded was that I was more curious -- but not because I had been born that way. If you watch little kids, they are intensely curious, always exploring and trying to figure out how things work. The problem is that school drives all that curiosity out. Instead of letting you explore things for yourself, it tells you that you have to read these particular books and answer these particular questions. And if you try to do something else instead, you'll get in trouble. Very few people's curiosity can survive that. But, due to some accident, mine did. I kept being curious and just followed my curiosity. First I got interested in computers, which led me to get interested in the Internet, which led me to get interested in building online news sites, which led me to get interested in standards (like RSS), which led me to get interested in copyright reform (since Creative Commons wanted to use similar standards). And on and on. Curiosity builds on itself -- each new thing you learn about has all sorts of different parts and connections, which you then want to learn more about. Pretty soon you're interested in more and more and more, until almost everything seems interesting. And when that's the case, learning becomes really easy -- you want to learn about almost everything, since it all seems really interesting. I'm convinced that the people we call smart are just people who somehow got a head start on this process. I fell like the only thing I've really done is followed my curiosity wherever it led, even if that meant crazy things like leaving school or not taking a "real" job. This isn't easy -- my parents are still upset with me that I dropped out of school -- but it's always worked for me.” (Aaron Swartz)</p></blockquote>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/no-thing-pure-hard-problem</guid><title>There is no such Thing as a Pure Hard Problem</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/no-thing-pure-hard-problem</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From time to time I use the differentiation between hard and soft problems or difficulties vs. messes and the TROPICS test from McCalman and Paton to differentiating these two. Why? The answer is simple. My first studies were engineering disciplines. Engineering disciplines are working with hard problems, that is problems where you have a clear understanding of what constitutes the problem and where you know when you solved the problem. However, at latest when you finish your studies you realize that life is far more complex. You might realize that two opposing and mutually exclusive solutions to the same problem might be correct, which makes you think about how well defined the problem is - a “soft problem”.</p><img src="images/thoughts/TROPICS-1.png"/><p>This is easy to see. But there was a piece missing. I worked in teams that did a great job in solving a tricky hard problem just to see that nobody acted on our results. It took me a while until my MBA teacher Nigel hit the nail when we told me “There is no such thing as a pure hard problem”. Every relevant hard problem is embedded in a real life context. And you have to understand the full context. If you solve the underlying hard problem you might simply solve the wrong problem. And looking back, I was part of several of those activities.</p><p>As I am now working in a project portfolio management function this is an important lesson. If you solve the wrong problem you are very inefficient, regardless on how well the project proceeds. <em>Thanks Nigel.</em></p><p>[Update 26/5/2017] The TROPICS Test was introduced to me to differentiate Hard from Soft problems. In the years following I found out that "soft problems" are often called "wicked problems". <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horst_Rittel">Horst Rittel</a> must have coined that term and he was creating a planning/design method known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Issue-Based_Information_System "Issue-Based Information System"">Issue-Based Information System</a> (IBIS) for handling wicked problems. IBIS made a lot of sense to me which is why I have created "<a href="https://kneupner.de/software/visual-thinking-ibis">Visual Thinking with IBIS</a>" as a tool supporting the IBIS Notation.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/switch-to-new-blog-side</guid><title>Switch to new blog side</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/switch-to-new-blog-side</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I changed my blog side. It is now integrated into my webpage <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/">www.kneupner.de</a>. New material will be published there. Old material is converted manually. Therefore not everything is available yet through my "new" blog side.<br>If you have subscribed to this blog, then please add now the new feed <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/files/feed.xml">http://www.kneupner.de/files/feed.xml</a><br>See you on <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/">www.kneupner.de</a>...</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/thebigrocks</guid><title>Steven Covey: The Big Rocks</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/thebigrocks</link><pubDate>Sun, 9 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I got an email with another great video I would like to share. This time it is Steven Covey, maybe best known for his book “7 Habits of highly effective people”. Watch, laugh and learn.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VyL93MlR_I0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p>I referred already several times to the blog of JD Meier. He is a big fan of Steven Covey teaching. Have a look at his blog, e.g.</p><ul><li><a href="http://sourcesofinsight.com/stephen-covey-leaves-a-legacy/">http://sourcesofinsight.com/stephen-covey-leaves-a-legacy/</a></li><li><a href="http://sourcesofinsight.com/stephen-covey-quotes">http://sourcesofinsight.com/stephen-covey-quotes</a></li></ul>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/flying-logic-for-visual-thinking</guid><title>Flying Logic for Visual Thinking</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/flying-logic-for-visual-thinking</link><pubDate>Sat, 5 May 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago, I was pointed towards a software tool called "<a href="http://flyinglogic.com/">Flying Logic</a>" from Sciral. I was told that Flying Logic would support to plan backwards from the goal. I like software that helps me to display my thoughts (I call that "Visual Thinking") and I fully subscribe to the thinking backwards idea (famously promoted by Stephen Covey's "7 habits for highly successful people" as "<a href="https://www.stephencovey.com/7habits/7habits-habit2.php">Begin with the End in Mind</a>").</p><table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" style="float: right; text-align: right;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><div style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="320" src="images/TOCWithFlyingLogic.png">TOC mindmap</a> - another way of "Visual Thinking". By now I use Flying Logic regularly and use my mindmap as a guide to the eBook and to TOC.&nbsp;</div><div><br></div><table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" style="float: left; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.kneupner.de/VisualThinking/TOCWithFlyingLogic.png" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="247" src="images/TOCWithFlyingLogic.png" width="400"></a></td></tr><tr><td style="text-align: center;">Mindmap: Theory of Constraints with Flying Logic</td></tr></tbody></table><div>TOC provides different model types that help you focus on different aspects. Two of these models are the "Current Reality Tree", which is used to analyse the weaknesses of the current situation, and the "Future Reality Tree", which is used to envision a future solution. The latter, the Future Reality Tree, is actually the model type that let to me learning about Flying Logic. You start with the goal and analyse from there backwards how to achieve that goal. The provided grammar helps to think in a constructive way.</div><div><br></div><div>Overall, Flying Logic is a simple tool that allows you to display your thoughts. It comes with strong support for a backward thinking ("Begin with the End in Mind") due to the underlying theoretical framework TOC. My understanding to the framework is available <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/VisualThinking/TOCWithFlyingLogic.png">here</a>&nbsp;as a mindmap. But Flying Logic is not limited to the framework and you can easily create your own graphs types. The tool isn't cheap, but it was worth the money for me.&nbsp;</div><div><br></div></td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/business-motivation-model</guid><title>Business Motivation Model</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/business-motivation-model</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I mentioned the Business Motivation Model earlier. The <a href="http://www.businessrulesgroup.org/bmm.shtml">Business Motivation Model</a> is a model that explains core terminology for an organisation. The model is an <a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/BMM/">OMG</a> standard.<br><br>I got aware of the model during a conference when one of the main authors (the Business Rules expert <a href="http://www.ronross.info/">Ronald Ross</a>) explained it briefly. It doesn't surprise that he uses the model to explain how <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_rule">Business Rules</a> fit into an organisation.<br><br>I used the model to define the strategy of our department. The big advantage is that it explains easily the difference between concepts like "Vision", "Mission", "Goal", "Objective", "Strategy", and "Tactic". Having the clear distinction of these terms facilitates discussions that allow focusing on the "why" behind your activities. The terminology and relationships between the concepts provided by the model make it simple to see the bigger picture and how everybody's work relate to our goals.<br><br>The model includes further related concepts as can be seen from the diagram on the right side.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/the-why</guid><title>The "Why"</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/the-why</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes, so see/hear/learn something that immediately connects with some loose ends that you have in your mind. During my MBA did "learn" about the importance of strategy. How everybody needs to understand the connection between the current work and the overall direction. Every now and then you can extend your understanding. On a conference in June about EA and BPM for example, did I learn about the "<a href="http://www.businessrulesgroup.org/bmm.shtml">Business Motivation Model</a>" which can be used to describe the main concepts like vision, mission, goals, and strategies. And now, on my "Leading Others" course, this video was shown. Another tidbit, that connects some pieces of the puzzle. Enjoy.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://embed.ted.com/talks/simon_sinek_how_great_leaders_inspire_action" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-veronica-decides-to-die</guid><title>New Mindmap: Veronica Decides to Die</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-veronica-decides-to-die</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/LifePhilosophy.png"/><p>I created this mindmap whilst I was reading the book "Veronica Decides to Die" from Paulo Coelho. It is a book that makes you think about what you do with your life. Are you living your dream? Do you dare to fulfil your dreams?<br><br>I added a few own annotations to the mindmap.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/the-dancing-guy</guid><title>The Dancing Guy</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/the-dancing-guy</link><pubDate>Tue, 8 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a training course today on leadership. I was shown the following video clip. Enjoy!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-information-rules</guid><title>New Mindmap: Information Rules</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-information-rules</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/InformationRules.png"/><p><a href="http://www.blogger.com/"></a>I added a new mindmap on my website. This one covers the first chapter of a book on the nature of the information business. It shows some interesting aspects that everybody has to keep in mind when developing a business model on information. Why only the first chapter? Because it is the overview chapter. If you are interested in more on a specific topic, just read the according chapter.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-enterprise-architecture-as-a-strategy</guid><title>New Mindmap: Enterprise Architecture as a Strategy</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-enterprise-architecture-as-a-strategy</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/EnterpriseArchitectureAsAStrategy.png"/><p>I released another of my mindmaps. This is on an Enterprise Architecture book that I can recommend for people working in the EA area or for people coming from the business side to IT. I refer to the 4 maturity stages on a regular base as the model sets the scene for much of my current work.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/eac-bpm-2011-conference-in-london</guid><title>EAC BPM 2011 Conference in London</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/eac-bpm-2011-conference-in-london</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just came back from the <a href="http://www.irmuk.co.uk/eac2011/">Enterprise Architecture</a> and <a href="http://www.irmuk.co.uk/bpm2011/">Business Process Modelling</a> Conference(s) in London. I met a couple of interesting people and was able to listen to some well known people.<br>Key lessons that got reinforced on the conference:<br><br><br>- The problems are always the same, and it is never a hard problem, but always a soft problem (<a href="http://www.evernote.com/shard/s8/sh/9698e950-8a60-43f9-b1ca-1d09171e2c33/c5c8042f198bb7d66b5c436ea99e0d63">TROPICS</a>).</p><ul><li>BPM is very close to Organisational Development (OD).</li><li>EA and BPM are similar in many ways and very political. Governance, strategy, measurement and incentives are key concepts for both.</li><li>Don't boil the ocean. Better stay with a specific approach/activity and stick with it than starting everything at the same time.</li></ul><p>I hope I find the time to write in more detail about the conference.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/knowing-a-bit-more-about-myself</guid><title>Knowing a bit more about myself</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/knowing-a-bit-more-about-myself</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most interesting things in life for me is to understand myself better. How do I react to my environment? And why do I react the way you do? Since I started thinking about myself I am able to work on myself. Patterns arise and understanding grows. Knowing myself allows me to playing to my strengths and therefore improves my personal happiness.</p><p>One of the things that I enjoy are self-assessments. A good self-assessment explains some facets of your personality. The most interesting for me was the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myers-Briggs_Type_Indicator">Myers-Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI)</a>. In case you are interested: I wrote my personal result on my <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/Klaus/Private_Me.html">webpage</a>. The quickest assessment so far was a <a href="http://www.piworldwide.com/Products/Predictive-Index-System.aspx">PI</a> assessment that I had to provide prior to my interview for my current job. HR draw a very precise picture of me just on the base of a few selections of mine. Stunning! I found another interesting test a couple of days ago. It is called <a href="http://www.personaldna.com/">PersonalDNA</a>. I quite enjoyed it and realised that the results are consistent with what I know about myself. I quite like as well the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johari_window">Johari Window</a>. Make your own Johari Window <a href="http://kevan.org/johari">here</a>.</p><p>Good luck on your own journey to yourself. Clearly, assessments are only a small step on the way. But nonetheless, please let me know if you know good assessments.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/bruce-silver-bpmn-method-style-mindmap-for-level-1</guid><title>Bruce Silver: BPMN Method &amp; Style, Mindmap for Level 1</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/bruce-silver-bpmn-method-style-mindmap-for-level-1</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img src="images/visuals/BPMNLevel1.png"/> <figcaption>BPMN Level 1 Mind Map</figcaption></figure><p>I currently think a lot about the automation of workflows. Therefore, it is not surprising that I read about the topic. And as usual, I try to create a mind map to be able to remember what I read. This mind map is capturing (what I think) are the essentials for the first model (Level 1) of the method of the author.</p><p>Depending on my time, more mind maps will result from this book.</p><p><em>2023/9/20:</em> I didn't find the time to create more mind maps from this book. Sorry!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/10-common-happiness-mistakes</guid><title>10 Common Happiness Mistakes</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/10-common-happiness-mistakes</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just read a blog entry from Gretchen Rubin on common happiness mistakes (http://www.happiness-project.com/happiness_project/2010/11/10-common-happiness-mistakes.html) and suggest that you read it as well.<br><br>In general, I can recommend to look around on her site. The web side is a resource full of interesting thoughts. Have a look at her "Happiness Project" book. It contains a structured approach to happiness! Further interesting reads are her secrets of adulthood (http://www.happiness-project.com/happiness_project/secrets-of-adulthood.html) or her twelve personal commandments (on the left side on the page)</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/introducing-evernote-site-memory</guid><title>Introducing Evernote Site Memory</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/introducing-evernote-site-memory</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Did it ever happen to you that you said: "I have read something about this in the web?" Where you ever curious what it was? Let me tell you: in the last year I was always able to find it again. How? I no longer rely on bookmarks to find pages I was interested again. Bookmarks can become outdated. I store the whole page content!<br><br>I added a new gadget to my blog. The Evernote Site Memory button allows you to store my blogs quickly in your Evernote account.<br><br>What is Evernote? Evernote became my searchable memory, my external brain. If you are a knowledge worker like me you would often like to remember the content of the page you've once read. A friend at work wanted to tell me something about the a specific IT topic. He went and looked up all the bookmarks he had tagged with the topic. Of five pages one was still accessible. He was only able to provide me with a 5th of what he thought was worth remembering on the topic. I would have been able to provide all five pages.<br><br>Evernote allows you to store any webpage (in fact any data) into a repository. Right from the browser. Once set up you only click the Evernote button and the page is saved. You can than search within Evernote and find it again. You can browse or search search for a word within the content, like "GTD". Evernote does even an OCR scan on your pictures, recognising text in the picture. Next time you want to find a picture of a mindmap, I hope you put it into Evernote. If it says "Crucial Conversation" on the mindmap Evernote will find it for you. Evernote can be accessed in a web only manner, or with a client on your computer.<br><br>Actually, Evernote does more than storing web content for me. I scan in my paper stuff nowadays. Since I pay for the premium account (45$ a year), Evernote does OCR on my scanned PDFs. Looking for an old bill? Thames Water? I just type in "Thames Water" and it comes up. I use it with a Fujitsu ScanSnap S300M. The combination is fantastic: scanning of several pages takes only seconds. Within a minute, I can start searching within the document. At home. And through the web if I am currently on holidays.<br><br>Are you interested? Well, just click the green remember button with the Evernote elephant logo and start memorising. Enjoy!<br><br>[Update 30/09/2010]: Now I get my personal results included in every of my Google searches: http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/EvernoteBlog/~3/Q3kxfLvda8s/</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/creativity-by-john-cleese</guid><title>Creativity by John Cleese</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/creativity-by-john-cleese</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>John Cleese on creativity on YouTube.</p><div class="embeddedVideo"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y70nbDJI5Uk" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p>Key lessons for me:<br>* The unconscious mind is working in your favour - if you let it.<br>* We don't know where our ideas are coming from.<br>* You need boundaries in time and space to be productive/creative<br>* "To know how good you are at something requires the same skills as it does to be good at that thing." And this has implications...</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/the-elephant-and-the-rider</guid><title>The Elephant and the Rider</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/the-elephant-and-the-rider</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From time to time you come across ideas that make a strong impression on you. Often enough, it takes a while to fully understand that the information took such an important role in your life. But you realise that you come back to the idea and find it useful. Useful to interpret certain aspects of your life.<br><br>One of these ideas in my life is the <a href="http://sourcesofinsight.com/2010/04/21/the-elephant-and-the-rider/">elephant and rider metaphor</a>. I nearly missed this great blog entry of JD Meier, because it happened that I only got aware of the metaphor by reading a <a href="http://sourcesofinsight.com/2010/05/06/direct-the-rider-motivate-the-elephant-and-shape-the-path/">follow-up blog entry</a> the other day. I strongly recommend these two entries. (And I do recommend to follow the blog of JD Meier.)<br><br>To describe the idea in my own words: An elephant rider is generally able to direct the much larger elephant. But s/he won't be able to do that against the will of the elephant. In such a case the elephant will follow its own needs, leaving the rider in a helpless position. This relationship can be used to describe your rational mind (rider) versus your feelings (elephant). Did you ever try to change an unwanted behaviour? How often did you give in to your feelings and gave up on your (new year's) resolutions?<br><br>You won't be able to succeed in your personal goals if you can't bring your emotions in line. If it is your will against your emotions you will loose. You will have to influence your emotions if you want to change yourself, ie change unwanted behaviour. You might be able to get your elephant on the road with will power, but you will were out, eventually.<br><br>Why is this idea so interesting to me? Because it suddenly helps you to understand the world better. Why a positive attitude is paramount for changing a behaviour. It tells me what I did wrong so many times.<br><br>Take <a href="http://prezi.com/iytz6rithhih/change-or-die/">Change or die!</a> from Patrick Mayfield. I saw his presentation a while ago and it made an impression on me. He referenced the work from Alan Deutschman and took bypass patients as an example. According to his statistics a shocking 90% of patients are not changing there unhealthy behaviour (smoking!) after an bypass surgery, ensuring the next life-threatening situation in a few years. Why? Rider vs. elephant! The fact that you will die soon can't be translated into the language of the elephant. The patients knew they had to change but they didn't do it. A second study showed a far better rate of behavioural changes after focusing on positive emotions. For the second study people were given positive attitude to a behavioural change by connecting the change (give up smoking) with things they would like to do: playing with grand-children, being able to walk for an hour, etc. Being able to do things that create positive emotions does the trick. This is the language of your elephant, and is therefore influencing the elephant! This approach aligns your emotions with your abstract thinking and gives your rides the tools to stay on track. Focus on the positive aspects of the change.<br><br>Did you ever realise that people are not acting in a logical manner? I think I know why. The elephant is stronger. People do what feels right, not what they know is right. And if you want to do what is right the metaphor might be able to help you. Please let me know if you have more examples.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/strategy-vs-utility</guid><title>Strategy vs Utility</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/strategy-vs-utility</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Martin Fowler, one of the most influential people in the IT area, voiced once again an interesting opinion. You can read the full article here: http://martinfowler.com/bliki/UtilityVsStrategicDichotomy.html<br><br>In short, he says that you should be aware whether an IT project is just a utility or an strategic differentiator. The part that made me write this was his opinion on utility software. He phrases it like this:<br><br><br>&gt; My view is that for a utility function you buy the package and adjust your business process to match the software.</p><p>I haven't heard it that radical. But after some thinking, I agree. I guess in many cases it is easier and cheaper to make changes to your processes than to develop the perfect software for your current process. I would even expect that utility software is designed to support best practise. You might implement best practise in an non-strategic area just by adjusting your processes around standard software.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/moving-on</guid><title>Moving On!</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/moving-on</link><pubDate>Mon, 5 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I left once again Oxford. Four years of time spend in Oxford are finally history. No further visits planned.<br><br>I took my chance of this last weekend and had once again a close look. It is such a lovely town. A great place to live. My life took some great turns there... Thank you Oxford! And of course a big "thank you" to all the great people I met there. I learned so much from you.<br><br>Oxford is one of these amazing places where people are coming together. So many people are coming for a few months or years. They are eager to meet other people. They come with so different backgrounds and ideas. Some stay and add to the mixture. Others lived in Oxford all their lucky life.<br><br>I also enjoyed the rich cultural program. I personally loved the Catweazle Club (http://catweazleclub.org/) best. It has now even spin-offs in NY, London and Brighton! Do I need to say more?<br><br>So, it is time to let go. Take what was best, learn from the not-so-good and relax. It is not so much about where you live, it is about how well you know yourself. As long as you know yourself, you will be happy. But it helps when you like where you live: Copenhagen, here I am! :-)</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/found/creativity-methods</guid><title>Creativity Methods</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/found/creativity-methods</link><pubDate>Thu, 1 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While my MBA we discussed the relationship between innovation and change in the context of our module "Organisational Innovation and Change". The module discussed concepts like paradigms (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradigm) and the difference between difficulties and messes (see TROPICS Test from McCalman and Paton (2000): <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Change-Management-Guide-Effective-Implementation/dp/0761964991/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&s=books&qid=1270131357&sr=1-1"><em>Change Management: A Guide to Effective Implementation</em></a>).<br><br>One element that kept stuck with me is that change does happen anyway and you should embrace it to your advantage. In case you are interested in creativity techniques have a look at this page: <a href="http://www.mycoted.com/Category:Creativity_Techniques">http://www.mycoted.com/Category:Creativity_Techniques</a><br><br>I got the link today from Christine. Thanks a lot!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-project-startup</guid><title>New Mindmap: Project Startup</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-project-startup</link><pubDate>Thu, 1 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/ProjectManagement.png"/><p>I found an interesting article in a magazine about the approach a freelancer takes whenever she enters a new project. I liked the questionnaire, which I didn't want to forget.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-on-crucial-conversations</guid><title>New Mindmap on Crucial Conversations</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/new-mindmap-on-crucial-conversations</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="images/visuals/CrucialConversations2.png"/><p>Just uploaded my mindmap of <a href="http://www.kneupner.de/Klaus/MindMaps.html">"Crucial Conversations"</a>. I wish I would have read the book years ago. It is one of these books that connects so many things together that you already know. Hardly anything of it is new. And still it is the first time these "no-brainers" are collected and put into context. And suddenly it all makes sense. Give it a try!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/visual/project-management-mindmap</guid><title>Project Management Mindmap</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/visual/project-management-mindmap</link><pubDate>Tue, 9 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I use MindMaps to structure my thoughts on a regular base. Sometimes I use them to summarise books I like. I decided that I will share a few of these. Please keep in mind that I usually don’t intend to map the full book, but only what I think is really helpful. Use them on your own risk.<br><img src="images/visuals/Project-Startup.png"/> I will start with a small mind map on project management. It is my understanding of a small book from the "Pocketbook" series (Management Pocketbook Ltd.). I really liked the book because it connected of so many useful models.<br></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/Seeing-yourself</guid><title>Seeing yourself</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/Seeing-yourself</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I had a defeating experience. And as so often, I can learn a lot from it. I thought I created an programming setup that would allow others to use my work easily and efficiently. Well, it didn't work out. Today, I had to see how somebody without my level of expertise was able to screw the whole setting up, causing me up to two hours trying to get it working again. I apologised a lot. I felt very much ashamed. The other one will never use my setup.<br><br>How did it get so far? I forgot all the pain I had while becoming an expert. Like learning to drive a bike. It becomes so easy you forget how difficult (and even painful) it was to reach that level of expertise that allows you to drive everywhere. Clearly it's easy from there to transport stuff on the bike if that person provides you with the right equipment. But you still need to be able to drive that bike from A to B. No way around.<br><br>What did I do in the last months? I added complexity to my company. I created something that nobody will ever use. It is too difficult to even start with. I shouldn't do anything that is too complex. Small steps. Understandable steps. I can't stand it. I can't make big leaps...<br><br>... unless I really teach everybody exactly how to use my stuff. But how? It demands a lot of effort. How to convince others that it's worth to do so?</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/teach-how-to-think-not-what-to-think</guid><title>Teach "How to think", not "What to think"</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/teach-how-to-think-not-what-to-think</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read something interesting today. It was a story about a guy who tought the chairman of Intel Andy Grove about a problem that Intel faced. The interesting bit is how he taught it. Instead of telling the chairman the problem he explained first a model that he uses. In a second step he showed how to apply the model in a different sector (steel sector). The chairman understood the consequences for Intel on his own as a third step.<br><br>The interesting part is that the author (Clayton Christensen) is convinced that he wouldn't have been heard if he would have told Grove directly his message. For anyone who wants to read it as well, look at "Making Strategy Work", from the Lessons Learned series, 50 Lessons, Boston, pp. 31-38.<br>This links in with everything else I learned in the last months. It is quite similar to the persuasive funnel from Gillen (Terry Gillen (1999): Agreed! Improve your powers of influence, IPD). Both avoid to influence through direct teaching.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/there-are-lessons-everywhere-today-on-the-menu-dancing</guid><title>There are lessons everywhere. Today on the menu: dancing</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/there-are-lessons-everywhere-today-on-the-menu-dancing</link><pubDate>Wed, 7 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, I tried again to go dancing. A while ago (about 2 years ago) I decided it's finally time to learn dancing. It fitted well and -to be honest- it helped that my friends had a similar idea. So I went Salsa dancing for a while. Every week. It was fun, but to be honest, I liked the social bit more. And that bit got more difficult, since the course was up to three hours. Beginners started, the next hour was for intermediates, the third hour for experts - at least from my point of view, since I never made it. Eventually, I started some other private things and had no time anymore.<br><br>Obviously, if I would have liked it better, I would have continued. But I didn't really made progress. Neither in Salsa (difficult to start with), nor in Ceroc. Ceroc is much easier than Salsa. But even in Ceroc lessons I always reached the stage where I felt odd. I couldn't do the same moves over and over. For two simple reasons:<br>* it's boring, I guess as well for my partner. Somehow, I even loose the order of the moves, I'm that bored/unconcentrated/not into it. And I have no clue how to get back in track. Strange situations are the result.<br>* as soon as the partner knows the move as well (or even learns it as well), she is already moving as she should, not as I lead her. Therefore, I wasn't sure whether I led her or not.<br><br>Today, after nearly half a year without dancing lessons, I tried it again. Similar feelings. But today I left before it got really awkward. Instead, I thought about my dancing for the very first time. I thought about whether it was good to leave once without feeling ashamed. I thought about that I tried today to ask an experienced dancer to show me how she really knows what I intend for her to do. That was good. I felt a bit like a quitter. That was bad.<br><br>And then I realised something. I read a blog a while ago about <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/SourcesOfInsight/~3/492710220/">learning</a> from <a href="http://sourcesofinsight.com/">Sources of Insight</a>. In that article is a brief theory on learning based on two dimensions and two different ways of learning for each dimension: abstract or concrete and sequential or random. And now, it's so simple. These dancing lessons are not fitting to my learning style! All this time, I try to learn dancing by examples. The lesson is concrete practise and the moves are more or less in random order (maybe selected by difficulty, but more by how it looks like). Instead I need an abstract introduction. I need an overview of all the possibilities first. Otherwise i can't really use it and forget everything what I learned until the next week.<br><br>The positive result for me is instantaneously. I have a plan what to do next lesson. And once again I learned two important lessons.<br>1) If something doesn't work out, think about why it doesn't work. It's that simple.<br>2) To have a framework in the back of your mind is helpful. Too many things are not processed in my mind, because I don't have a hook to grab them. They pass by unnoticed. Once I heard something on a topic, I get sensibly. Once I'm sensibly for something, I can include it in my thoughts. In this case, I'm still not sure what class I fall into for the learning. Definitely the abstract learning, but I don't know yet whether I need random or sequel data. But that doesn't matter. I will find it out or will ignore the second dimension of the learning framework eventually if it doesn't matter for me. But what is important, it made me think the next time I had a problem form that area.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://kneupner.de/thoughts/one-week-free</guid><title>One Week Free</title><description></description><link>https://kneupner.de/thoughts/one-week-free</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had one week free of work. That means obviously my normal work, but as well my MBA studies. What happened during that time?<br><br>- I wasn't really relaxed.</p><ul><li>I didn't really know what to do. I wasn't bored. It was more like: I should have used the time better.</li><li>I didn't understand how to focus on me and my needs (body &amp; soul needs)</li></ul><p>and:<br><br>- I had time for myself. Even not knowing what would be best I did what I wanted to do.</p><ul><li>I had time to waste without thinking what I should do.</li><li>My partner showed me all her love by not demanding anything.</li></ul><p>What can I learn from this experiment?<br><br>- It takes time to calm down.</p><ul><li>It's not easy to fill time if you hardly had any time before.<ul></ul></li></ul><ul><li>It's good to discuss your situation with somebody who cares.<ul></ul></li></ul><ul><li>My body needs some action. The trip to the Cotswolds was great.<ul></ul></li></ul><p>Implications for next time?<br><br>- Expect less</p><ul><li>Go away, so you can't do anything and you don't even realise that you don't have anything meaningful to do. But do it like my friend Nick. 2 weeks Disneyland. There is hardly anything to do.<ul></ul></li></ul><ul><li>Have a good book.<ul></ul></li></ul><ul><li>Book stores are always great.<ul></ul></li></ul><ul><li>Enjoy the small things in life.</li><li>Do some physical exercises: walking, cycling, swimming, running.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>